# **Amit Kumar Singh**

Full Stack Developer

Ranchi, Jharkhand
(+91) 82100-98916
amitsin6h@gmail.com.com
https://www.linkedin.com/in/amitsin6h/
https://github.com/amitsin6h
https://stackoverflow.com/users/5892547/amitsin6h

Self-taught computer programmer and love to do code contributions in open source projects. I have 2+ years work experience specializing in backend/infrastructure, web development and security. Interested in devising a better problem-solving method for challenging tasks, and learning new technologies and tools if the need arises.

# **Work Experience**

## Founder, Fullstack Developer

Jan 2019 - Present

Feelin

#### V2.1.0 - V3.0.0

- Updated the complete UI/UX of the app using React Native, and other third-party libraries
- Updated the backend using Apollo, Graphql, Express
- Designed the product website using MERN stack
- Implemented Redis caching technique
- Updated MongoDB schema for the product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker containers.

#### V1.0.0 - 2.1.0

- Developed the complete UI/UX of the product using React Native and other third party libraries
- Designed the product website using HTML, CSS, and other javascript libraries.
- Implemented RESTful API server using Expressis and Nodejs
- Implemented API request validation using JsonWebtoken
- Implemented API caching technique to handle requests
- Implemented Flynn PaaS to manage product on production
- Designed advance schema for the complete product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker container, Flynn PaaS( Open Source focusing on high-availability, fault tolerance, and auto-scaling

# Software Engineer Intern

Sep 2018 - Aug 2019

cloudyBoss

 Cloud programming (both client and server-side)
 Application Programming Interfaces, Agile methodologies and UML, Object Oriented Programming, UI/UX design

# Education

**MBA, IT & Systems** 2019 - 2021

IMS, Ranchi University

 Selected for "Business English for Young Professional Workshop" conducted by U.S Embassy

**BBA, Marketing** 2015 - 2018

Marwari College, Ranchi University

**AISSCE, Commerce** 2013 - 2015

Central Academy, Bariatu

**AISSE** 2013

Army Public School, Ranchi

 Completed 2 years (2010-2012) in Army wing 3JH BN NCC Ranchi as Lance Corporal/ Corporal.

#### **Tech Articles**

- **C#Corner:**<a href="https://www.c-sharpcorner.com/members/amit-singh262/articles">https://www.c-sharpcorner.com/members/amit-singh262/articles</a>
- LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/amitsin">https://www.linkedin.com/in/amitsin</a> 6h/detail/recent-activity/posts/

## Certifications

- 2019, cloudyBoss accreditation cBX82 Technology
- 2017, Red Hat Certified System Administrator
- 2017, Red Hat Certified Specialist in Ansible Automation
- 2016, Intro to Python for Data Science, DataCamp

## Founder, Fullstack Developer

Jan 2018 - Nov 2018

Devconsole

- Developed the complete UI/UX of the product
- Designed the REST API server using Expressis and Nodejs
- Implemented API request validation using
- Designed MongoDB schema for the complete product
- Built and deployed overall service infrastructure utilizing Docker container, Flynn PaaS

#### Research Intern

Jun 2018 - Jul 2018

LinuxWorld Informatics Pvt Ltd

- SAAS(Software As A Service) A one-click implementation
  was achieved which provided the clients Firefox browser
  and VLC media player software on their systems from
  DOCKERS running on the cloud server.
- STAAS(Storage As A Service)
  - Block Storage In Block storage we used ISCSI Protocol to provide clients with block storage available at the cloud to be used at the client system.
  - Object Storage In Object storage, using NFS and SSHFS Protocol to provide user fixed storage overcloud.
- CAAS(Container As A Service) A one-click launch, starting, stopping and removing and providing the terminal of docker container was achieved.
- PAAS(Platform As A Service) A one-click launch of a python platform was provided for clients where they can code as they wish.
- **Hadoop** A CGI based web portal was developed for a one-click setup of hdfs and map-reduce cluster depending on the requirements of the client per se, the size of the cluster required, and the number of processors required for the big data analysis.
- Machine Learning The web service for the client was secured by Face recognition using machine learning and also included parts of speech recognition using python modules. IMAGE PROCESSING constitutes a large portion of the security aspect of the service.
- Ansible The entire configuration requirement of the project was met by the creation of ANSIBLE playbooks for both the client and the cloud.
- Dockers For the safe and secure single client-based service production, most of the services were provided through dockers only

## **Hackathons & Achievements**

- 2020, eLife Innovation Leader, eLife
- 2019, Intel Edge Al Scholar, Udacity
- 2019, Y Combinator Startup School
- 2018, OpenTechNights Winner, FOSSASIA
- 2017, Quality Assurance Contributor, Mozilla
- 2017, First, Hackathon De Corps
- 2016, **Second**, UTKRAANTI'16 with Padarth'16 IIT Bombay
- 2016, **Associate Trainer**, App Development Training for Nepalese
- 2015, **Top 10**, App Hackathon (Gov. of Jharkhand)

#### Skills

- Front-End: HTML5, CSS3, JS, JQuery, Bootstrap, AngularJS, ReactJS, React Native, Redux
- Back-End: NodeJS, GraphQL, Apollo, Python, php
- Web Server: Nginx, Apache
- Mobile App: React-Native, Android Studio, Ionic
- **Desktop App:** NW.js
- Database: NoSql, MySQL
- Web Framework: MERN Stack, MEAN Stack, Django, Flask, LAMP
- **Programming Lang.:** Python, JavaScript, php
- Version Control Tools: Git, Bitbucket
- PaaS: CloudJiffy, Dokku, Flynn
- DevOps: Ansible, Splunk
- Big Data: Hadoop, Hive, Spark, Splunk
- Data Analysis: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plottly
- Others: Web Security, OWASP TOP 10, Networking, Web Scraping, Linux, Quality Assurance, Data Mining

## **Projects**

Feelin - Share what you feel. The app is built using react native and backend using node js, expressjs, MongoDB and some other libraries. The reason why I built the app.

<u>Al Monkey</u> - Al-based web browser which consults users based on their search query. This project was shortlisted for <u>eLife Innovation Leader 2020</u>.

<u>MozCode Paste</u> - This project aims to paste code, share code and get the code reviewed. This project was shortlisted for <u>Mozilla Pulse</u>.

## **Digital Marketing Intern**

Jan 2018 - Feb 2018

Genesis Digisec

- Developed complete SEO and Google analytics for a wordpress website, also worked in UI/UX of the website
- Suggested online marketing strategy for the promotion of the website

#### Jr. Researcher

Feb 2017 - Aug 2017

Cyber Peace Foundation

- Worked in Indian Honeynet Project, web and application related projects
- Developed windows and Linux software using NodeWebkit

# Software Developer

Nov 2016 - Feb 2017

ResultsTrack Pvt. Ltd

- Involved in Data Visualization and Data Analysis projects, alon with some websites and web application projects
- Created an android app to collect survey in offline mode and automatically gets updated whenever the internet was connected

#### Intern

Aug 2016 - Nov 2016

Nathcorp Inc

 Involved in Data Visualization and Data Analysis projects and worked in dynamic graphs and maps using php and third party javascript library

#### Volunteer

## **Open-Source Contributor**

GirlScript Summer of Code <u>#Pull Request</u> <u>Merged</u>

 MEVN CLI: A CLI tool for getting started with the MEVN stack. It offers a super-simple boilerplate template and additional utilities for building a MEVN stack-based web app.

## Code Contributor #Pull Request Merged

PublicLab

 Code contribution for improving the PublicLab websites and its other projects for the community.

## Code Contributor #Pull Request Merged

PyCon India 2017

 Involved with the web development team for fixing the web related issues for the PyCon India 2017 website.

#### Code Contributor #Pull Request Merged

PyConf Hyderabad 2017

 Involved with the web development team for fixing the web related issues for the PyCon Hyd 2017 website.

#### **Club Leader**

HackClub

 Responsible for building a local community of developers in college and universities and organizing meet-ups.

#### Mozillian

Mozilla

 Event organizing for the community and creating FOSS Awareness. Built the Mozilla Jharkhand community website #Pull Request Merged. Quality Assurance contributor from the Mozilla India team.